Loretta Krupinski Papers
© 2007 University of Connecticut
Loretta Krupinski Papers.
1990-2002.
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center.
Krupinski, Loretta.
19.75 linear feet.
MSS19970116
The collection contains original and final artwork, sketches, correspondence, proofs, layouts, book dummies, illustrations, and galleys for twenty-three books illustrated by Loretta Krupinski.
Biography
Loretta Krupinski trained at the School of Art at Syracuse University. She worked in illustration and graphic design and was an editorial illustrator for Newsday. She is both a marine artist and an author/illustrator of twenty-nine books for children.
Published Works
Author/Illustrator
Best friends, Loretta Krupinski, 1998
Bluewater journal: the voyage of the Sea Tiger, Loretta Krupinski, 1995
Celia's island journal, Celia Thaxter, Loretta Krupinski, 1992
Heidi, Johanna Spyri, Loretta Krupinski, 1996
Lost in the fog, Irving Bacheller, Loretta Krupinski, 1990
New England scrapbook: a journey through poetry, prose, and pictures, Loretta Krupinski, 2002
Illustrator
Dear Rebecca, winter is here, Jean Craighead George, 1993
Fabulous frogs, Linda Glaser, 1999
How a seed grows, Helene J. Jordan, 1992
The Irish Cinderlad, Shirley Climo, 1996
Mouse of my heart: a treasury of sense and nonsense, Margaret Wise Brown, 2001
The Old ladies who liked cats, Carol Greene, 1991
The Runaway Christmas toy, Linda Hayward, 1994
Sailing to the sea, Mary Claire Helldorfer, 1991
The Story of Christmas, Barbara Cooney, 1995
Tiny green thumbs, C.Z. Guest, 2000
The Velveteen rabbit, or, How toys become real, Margery Williams, 1996
A Visit from St. Nicholas and Santa Mouse too!, Clement C. Mouse, 1998
Where is that cat?, Carol Greene, 1999
Why do leaves change color?, Betsy Maestro, 1994
Wonderful worms, Linda Glaser, 1992
Scope and Content
The collection contains original and final artwork, sketches, correspondence, proofs, layouts, book dummies, illustrations, and galleys for twenty-three books illustrated by Loretta Krupinski.
Arrangement
Research photographs and slides have been separated. The collection is arranged chronologically by publication date, although an alphabetical list of titles illustrated and/or authored by Krupinski is also included for cross reference.
Series I: Book Art ( 1991-2001 )
Series II: Research Photographs ( undated [1991-2001] )
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to children's literature and associated artwork. See especially, the papers of Betsy and Guilio Maestro and Barbara Cooney. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Index Terms
This record series is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Persons:
Krupinski, Loretta.
Subjects:
Children's literature, American--20th century.; Children's literature--illustrations.; Children's poetry, American--20th century.; Children's literature--Connecticut authors.; Children's literature--Connecticut illustrators.; Illustrated children's books.
Document Types:
Artwork.; Books.; Correspondence.; Drawings.; Galley proofs.; Illustrations.; Manuscripts.; Notes.; Photocopies.; Photographs.; Publications.; Sketches.; Typescripts.
Occupations:
Authors, American--Connecticut.; Illustrators, American.
Restrictions on Access
There are no access restrictions on this collection.
Acquisition Information
The collection was donated in March 1997 by Ms. Krupinski. An addition to the collection was made in 2001.
Detailed Description
- Series I: Book Art, undated, 1990-2002
  - Lost in the fog, Irving Bacheller, 1990
    - Correspondence, 1988-1989 (Box 1:, Folder 1)
    - Story text and jacket flap text drafts (Box 1:, Folder 1)
    - Sketches, original and photocopied (Box 4:, Folder 2)
    - Book dummies (2 items) (Box 1:, Folder 3)
    - Book reviews, 1990 (Box 1:, Folder 3)
  - The Old ladies who liked cats, Carol Greene, 1991
    - Correspondence, 1989 (Box 1:, Folder 4)
    - Story text (Box 1:, Folder 4)
    - Layout (Box 1:, Folder 4)
    - Sketches (Box 4:, Folder 5)
    - Final artwork (Box 4:, Folder 5)
  - Sailing to the Sea, Mary Claire Helldorfer, 1991
    - Correspondence, 1990 (Box 1:, Folder 6)
    - Layout (Box 1:, Folder 6)
    - Sketches (Box 4:, Folder 7)
    - Matted artwork (Box 4:, Folder 8)
    - Matted artwork (Box 4:, Folder 9)
    - Final artwork (Box 4:, Folder 10)
    - Color proofs (Box 1:, Folder 11)
  - Celia's island journal, Celia Thaxter, 1992
    - Research materials (Box 1:, Folder 12)
    - Story text drafts, 2 copies (Box 1:, Folder 13)
    - Book dummies (2 items) (Box 1:, Folder 14)
    - Sketches (Box 4:, Folder 15)
    - Final artwork (Box 4:, Folder 15)
    - Second proofs, pp. 7, 11, 13, 17, 18, 19, 21, 25, 29 (Box 1:, Folder 16)
    - Dustjacket proof (Box 1:, Folder 17)
    - Loose printed pages (Box 4:, Folder 18)
  - How a seed grows, Helene J. Jordan, 1992
    - Sketches (Box 5:, Folder 19)
    - Final artwork (Box 5:, Folder 20)
    - First proofs (Box 5:, Folder 21)
  - Wonderful Worms, Linda Glaser, 1992
    - Final artwork (Box 5:, Folder 22)
  - Dear Rebecca, winter is here, Jean Craighead George, 1993
    - Correspondence, 1992 (Box 1:, Folder 23)
    - Story text proof, pp. 4-5 (Box 1:, Folder 23)
    - Book dummies (2 items) (Box 1:, Folder 23)
    - Sketches (Box 5:, Folder 24)
    - Final artwork (Box 5:, Folder 24)
  - A New England Scrapbook, 1994
    - Correspondence, 1992 (Box 1:, Folder 25)
    - List of poems needing permission for inclusion (Box 1:, Folder 26)
    - Book dummy (Box 1:, Folder 27)
    - Original sketches (Box 5:, Folder 28)
    - Final artwork (Box 5:, Folder 28)
    - Book dummy (Box 1:, Folder 29)
    - Book dummies (2 items) (Box 1:, Folder 30)
    - Color proofs (Box 5:, Folder 31)
    - F and G (2 items) (Box 1:, Folder 32)
    - Photocopied book pages (Box 1:, Folder 33)
    - Publicity materials, 1994 (Box 1:, Folder 34)
  - The Runaway Christmas toy, Linda Hayward, 1994
    - Correspondence, 1994-1995 (Box 1:, Folder 35)
    - Original sketches (Box 5:, Folder 36)
    - Final artwork (Box 5:, Folder 36)
    - Dummy cover, illustration (Box 1:, Folder 37)
  - Why do Leaves change color?, Betsy Maestro, 1994
    - Sketches (Box 6:, Folder 38)
    - Early hand-drawn dummy with editor's comments (Box 2:, Folder 39)
    - Final artwork (Box 6:, Folder 40)
    - Dustwrapper (Box 2:, Folder 41)
    - 2 disbound signatures (Box 2:, Folder 41)
  - Bluewater journal: the voyage of the Sea Tiger, 1995
    - Correspondence, 1993 (Box 2:, Folder 42)
    - Research notes (Box 2:, Folder 43)
    - Story text (2 copies) (Box 2:, Folder 43)
    - Sketches (Box 6:, Folder 44)
    - Book dummies (2 items) (Box 2:, Folder 45)
    - Final artwork, color - pp. 12, 14, 16, 18, 26, 28 (Box 2:, Folder 46)
    - First and second proofs (Box 6:, Folder 47)
    - Final pages (Box 6:, Folder 48)
    - Dustjackets (Box 2:, Folder 49)
  - The Story of Christmas, Barbara Cooney, 1995
    - Correspondence (Box 2:, Folder 50)
    - Sketches (Box 6:, Folder 51)
    - Final artwork (Box 6:, Folder 51)
    - First proofs (Box 2:, Folder 52)
  - Heidi, Johanna Spyri, adapted by Loretta Krupinski, 1996
    - Correspondence, 1995 (Box 2:, Folder 53)
    - Notes on original novel, handwritten (Box 2:, Folder 54)
    - Story text drafts (Box 2:, Folder 55)
    - Sketches (Box 6:, Folder 56)
    - Book dummy (2 items) (Box 2:, Folder 57)
    - Dust jacket (Box 2:, Folder 58)
  - The Irish Cinderlad, Shirley Climo, 1996
    - Correspondence, 1994-1995 (Box 2:, Folder 59)
    - Story text drafts (Box 2:, Folder 59)
    - Sketches (Box 6:, Folder 60)
    - Final artwork (Box 6:, Folder 60)
  - The Velveteen Rabbit, Margery Williams Bianco, 1996
    - List of illustrations (Box 2:, Folder 61)
    - Final artwork (Box 6:, Folder 62)
  - Into the woods, 1997
    - Correspondence, 1996 (Box 3:, Folder 63)
    - Story text draft (Box 4:, Folder 64)
    - Book dummies (2 items) (Box 4:, Folder 64)
    - Sketches, photocopies (Box 7:, Folder 65)
  - Best Friends, 1998
    - Research notes (Box 2:, Folder 66)
    - Research notes (Box 2:, Folder 67)
    - Story text (Box 3:, Folder 68)
    - Sketches (Box 3:, Folder 69)
    - Dummies (Box 3:, Folder 70)
    - Final artwork (Box 7:, Folder 71)
    - First proofs (Box 7:, Folder 71)
  - A Visit from Saint Nicholas, and Santa Mouse Too!, Clement Clark Moore, adapted by Loretta Krupinski, 1998
    - Correspondence (Box 3:, Folder 72)
    - Book layout (Box 3:, Folder 72)
    - Sketches, photocopied (Box 3:, Folder 72)
    - Sketches (Box 7:, Folder 73)
    - Book dummies (4 copies) (Box 3:, Folder 74)
    - Final artwork (Box 7:, Folder 75)
  - Fabulous frogs, Linda Glaser, 1999
    - Correspondence, undated, 1998 (Box 3:, Folder 76)
    - Sketch photocopies (Box 3:, Folder 77)
    - Research materials (Box 3:, Folder 77)
    - Story text (Box 3:, Folder 77)
    - Layout (Box 3:, Folder 77)
    - Book dummy (Box 3:, Folder 77)
    - Sketches (Box 7:, Folder 78)
    - Final artwork (Box 7:, Folder 79)
  - Where is that Cat?, Carol Greene, 1999
    - Correspondence (Box 3:, Folder 80)
    - Layout (Box 3:, Folder 80)
    - Text (Box 3:, Folder 80)
    - Early sketches (Box 3:, Folder 81)
    - Sketches (Box 7:, Folder 82)
    - Illustration proofs (Box 7:, Folder 82)
    - Book dummies (4 copies) (Box 3:, Folder 83)
  - Tiny Green Thumbs, C.Z. Guest, 2000
    - Correspondence (Box 3:, Folder 84)
    - Illustration plan (Box 3:, Folder 84)
    - Sketches (Box 7:, Folder 85)
    - Sketches, photocopies (Box 7:, Folder 85)
    - Book dummies, 2 copies (Box 3:, Folder 86)
  - Mouse of my heart: a treasury of sense and nonsense, Margaret Wise Brown, 2001
    - Correspondence, 1999-2000 (Box 3:, Folder 87)
    - Story text drafts (Box 3:, Folder 87)
    - Original sketches (Box 3:, Folder 88)
    - Photocopies of sketches (Box 3:, Folder 88)
    - Preliminary layout (Box 3:, Folder 88)
    - Sketches (Box 8:, Folder 89)
    - Sketches (Box 8:, Folder 90)
    - Final artwork (Box 8:, Folder 91)
    - Final artwork (Box 8:, Folder 92)
    - Final artwork (Box 8:, Folder 93)
  - My world of color, Margaret Wise Brown, 2002
    - Correspondence, 1990 (Box 3:, Folder 94)
    - Preliminary sketches (Box 3:, Folder 94)
    - Story text draft (Box 3:, Folder 94)
    - Layout (Box 3:, Folder 94)
    - Book dummy (Box 3:, Folder 95)
      This dummy was preliminary, and contains chameleons instead of the mice that were used in the final book.
    - Sketches (Box 3:, Folder 96)
      Includes chameleon sketches.
    - Loose dummy pages (Box 3:, Folder 97)
- Series II: Research Photographs, undated [1991-2001]
  - A New England Scrapbook
    - Slides (3 items) (Box 9:, Folder 98)
  - Bluewater journal: the voyage of the Sea Tiger, 1995
    - Negatives (Box 9:, Folder 99)
    - Negatives (Box 9:, Folder 100)
    - Photographs (Box 9:, Folder 101)
    - Photographs (Box 9:, Folder 102)
  - Heidi
    - Photographs (Box 9:, Folder 103)
  - Best Friends, 1998
    - Photographs (Box 9:, Folder 104)